

#### RESEARCHER IN COMPUTATIONAL TRUST, PRIVACY, AND SECURITY

Diasta Ekoda no Mori 503, 2-20-3 Toyotama-kita, Nerima-ku, Tokyo 176-0012, Japan

□ (+81) 80-3315-8649 | 🗷 a.basu@xtremebytes.com | 💣 http://www.anirbanbasu.com | 🛅 anirbanbasu

"There is only one corner of the universe you can be certain of improving, and that's your own self." – Aldous Huxley

# Summary.

With more than a decade of research experience within both academia and industry, I have co-authored 70+ research papers and 25+ Japanese patents. My publications have been cited more than 1,200 times setting my overall h-index to 19 (source: Google Scholar). My research is based on a user-centric view of privacy; and computational trust as an information security paradigm in an increasingly knowledge-based connected world. The areas of research that interest me include, but are not limited to: computational trust systems, distributed consensus, privacy and risk, privacy preserving data mining, AI safety and causal models. I like working on complex problems that require multi-disciplinary approaches. Outside research and the related stuff, I am keen on photography, videography and the associated travels.

## Professional experience

**Hitachi, Ltd.**Yokohama, Japan

RESEARCHER

Oct. 2018 - present

• Summary: Researcher in computational trust systems at the Security Research Department within the Hitachi Research & Development group, which is a part of Hitachi, Ltd.

**Freelancer** Tokyo, Japan

CONSULTANT

Aug. 2014 – present

• Highlights: Open-source software development, web design and development, document design and photography.

**KDDI Research, Inc.**RESEARCHER ENGINEER

Fujimino, Japan

May. 2013 - Apr. 2018

• Highlights: Within the Information Security Laboratory, worked on (a) a multi-institutional EUR 3M EU-Japan Horizon 2020 funded project to realise a secure data storage and privacy-preserving analytics engine over heterogeneous multi-cloud environments spanning across national borders; and (b) a Toyota ITC and KDDI Research jointly funded collaborative project with ISTI-CNR and the University of Pisa on privacy risks in trajectory data.

Tokai University Tokyo, Japan

POST-DOCTORAL RESEARCHER

Oct. 2010 - Mar. 2013

• *Highlights:* Developed a privacy-preserving collaborative filtering scheme over encrypted domain and demonstrated the feasibility in real-world public cloud environments – the Google App Engine and the Amazon Elastic Beanstalk – as part of a multi-institutional JPY 500M+ Japanese government funded project on privacy-preserving data mining on the cloud.

University of Sussex

Brighton, UK

ASSOCIATE TUTOR (OCT. 2004 – JAN. 2010) AND RESEARCH FELLOW (OCT. 2008 – SEP. 2009)

Oct. 2004 – Jan. 2010

• Highlights: Re-developed a course module on electronic commerce technologies for the Masters degree programme funded by American Express. Worked in two (GBP 1M and GBP 1.4M) EPSRC funded research projects related to computational trust.

Freelancer Brighton, UK

TECHNOLOGY CONSULTANT (JUL. 2005 – SEP. 2008; JUN. 2010 – SEP. 2010)

Jul. 2005 - Sep. 2010

• Highlights: Technology consultant to the University of Sussex library. Developed Java Web Services hooks for Class Calendar Ltd. Codeveloped computational skills training videos for Claro Training Ltd.

University of Sussex

Brighton, UK

STEP SUMMER INTERN (Jul. 2003 – Aug. 2003) and then Research Assistant

Jul. 2003 - Sep. 2004

- *Highlights:* Developed a lightweight augmented reality based visualisation technology based on backend XML-based storage as part of a €2.8M EU Framework Programme V funded project on digital cultural heritage.
- Award: Shell Technology Enterprise Programme (STEP, UK) Local Finalist.

### Professional affiliations \_\_\_

#### **University of Sussex**

Brighton, UK

VISITING RESEARCH FELLOW

Jan. 2010 – present

· Collaborative research with the Foundations of Software Systems (FoSS) group in the Department of Informatics.

### IFIP Trust Management (IFIPTM)

Tokyo, Japan

PUBLICITY CHAIR (JUN. 2010 – JUN. 2015) AND SECRETARY (JUN. 2015 – PRESENT)

Jun. 2010 – present

• Contributing to the IFIP Working Group 11.11 – Trust Management (IFIPTM), the premier venue on computational trust management research.

**Rutgers University** 

Newark, NJ, USA

1 OF 2

Oct. 2014 - Sep. 2017

VISITING RESEARCH FELLOW

• Collaborative research with Prof. Jaideep Vaidya at the Rutgers Business School.

UPDATED: DECEMBER 22, 2019 ANIRBAN BASU | CURRICULUM VITÆ

### **Education**

### University of Sussex Brighton, UK

DOCTOR OF PHILOSOPHY (D.PHIL.) IN COMPUTER SCIENCE AND ARTIFICIAL INTELLIGENCE

Oct. 2004 - Feb. 2010

- Supervisors: Prof. Ian Wakeman and Dr. Dan Chalmers.
- Examiners: Dr. Des Watson (University of Sussex) and Prof. David Parish (Loughborough University)
- Doctoral thesis: 'A Reputation Framework for Behavioural History' proposed a high-level, generalised, policy-independent and context-aware framework to build and share reputations of network clients based on their behavioural history in order to inform future interactions. PDF: http://www.anirbanbasu.com/files/thesis-dphil2010.pdf.

University of Sussex

Brighton, UK

BACHELOR OF ENGINEERING (B.Eng.) IN COMPUTER SYSTEMS ENGINEERING

Oct. 2001 - Jun. 2004

- Grade: First Class Honours.
- Awards: (1) IEE Sussex Branch local prize for Outstanding Performance in Computer Systems Engineering (B.Eng.); and (2) the Eurotherm company prize for Best Electrical, Electronic or Computer Systems Engineering project.
- Final year project: 'ARCOLite a visualisation system for viewing museum artefacts' presented a lightweight XML-based repository and a desktop visualisation in both virtual and augmented reality. PDF: http://www.anirbanbasu.com/files/thesis-beng2004.pdf.

## **Accolades**

### INVITED TALKS

2018	World Wide Web Foundation, Privacy – connecting the dots	London, UK
2017	IFIP TM – Doctoral Symposium, Homomorphic Encryption – an answer to privacy?	Göteborg, Sweden
2015	<b>Kyushu University – Next Generation Cryptography</b> , Homomorphic Encryption – are we there yet?	Fukuoka, Japan
2012	<b>CSA – SecureCloud</b> , Practical privacy using homomorphic encryption – a myth or reality	Frankfurt, Germany

### **AWARDS**

2004	<b>IEE Sussex Branch local prize</b> , for Outstanding Performance in Computer Systems Engineering (B.Eng.)	Brighton, UK
2004	Eurotherm company prize, for Best Electrical, Electronic or Computer Systems Engineering project	Brighton, UK
2003	Local Finalist, Shell Technology Enterprise Programme (STEP)	Brighton, UK

#### SCHOLARSHIPS

2004	<b>Graduate Teaching Assistantship (2004–2007)</b> , Department of Informatics (University of Sussex)	Brighton, UK
2001	Dean's Bursary (2001–2004), Department of Engineering and Design (University of Sussex)	Brighton, UK

### **Publications**

A full list of publications is available at: http://www.anirbanbasu.com/#research.

#### **Research papers**

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

- [1] A. Al Omar, M. Z. A. Bhuiyan, **A. Basu**, S. Kiyomoto, and M. S. Rahman, "Privacy-friendly platform for healthcare data in cloud based on blockchain environment," *Future Generation Computer Systems*, 2019.
- [2] **A. Basu**, M. S. Rahman, R. Xu, K. Fukushima, and S. Kiyomoto, "VIGraph A Framework for Verifiable Information," in *Proceedings of the IFIP WG 11.11 International Conference on Trust Management (IFIPTM)*, Göteborg, Sweden, 2017, pp. 12–20.
- [3] **A. Basu**, A. Monreale, R. Trasarti, J. C. Corena, F. Giannotti, D. Pedreschi, S. Kiyomoto, Y. Miyake, and T. Yanagihara, "A risk model for privacy in trajectory data," *Journal of Trust Management*, vol. 2, no. 1, pp. 1–23, 2015.
- [4] J. Vaidya, I. Yakut, and **A. Basu**, "Efficient Integrity Verification for Outsourced Collaborative Filtering," in *Proceedings of the IEEE International Conference on Data Mining (ICDM)*, Shenzhen, China, 2014.
- [5] **A. Basu**, J. Vaidya, H. Kikuchi, and T. Dimitrakos, "Privacy-preserving collaborative filtering on the cloud practical implementation experiences," in *Proceedings of the IEEE Cloud*, Santa Clara, CA, USA, 2013.
- [6] **A. Basu**, S. Fleming, J. Stanier, S. Naicken, I. Wakeman, and V. K. Gurbani, "The state of peer-to-peer network simulators," *ACM Computing Surveys*, vol. 45, no. 4, pp. 46:1–46:25, 08 2013.

### Patents and public information (total 27)

WIPO PATENTSCOPE PUBLICATION NUMBERS

 $2019176264,\ 2019174995,\ 2019121946,\ 2019075619,\ 2018195907,\ 2018195154,\ 2018136625,\ 2018136626,\ 2018136627,\ 2018124513,\ 2018124924,\ 2018022258,\ 2017183932,\ 2017059872,\ 2017037180,\ 2016167705,\ 2016052047,\ 2016025563,\ 2016009243,\ 2015210795,\ 2015176496,\ 2015148907,\ 2015127859,\ 2015095671,\ 2015069350,\ 2015041863,\ 2015014958.$ 

### Skills\_\_\_

OS: MacOS, Windows, Linux, UNIX; Documents: MS Office, Google Docs and Etc.; Software development: Java, C#, Objective-C, Computing skills

C++, Visual C++, C, Visual Basic, XML, Javascript, UML, Subversion, Git, JUnit, Ant, Mayen, MySQL, JBoss, Tomcat, Google App

Engine, Amazon Elastic Beanstalk. (Non-exhaustive list.)

**Languages** English (fluent), Bengali (native), Japanese (elementary), Hindi (elementary)

UPDATED: DECEMBER 22, 2019 ANIRBAN BASU | CURRICULUM VITÆ 2 OF 2